Okay, so today's דף daf, *daf* is כ"ט *chaf tes*, 29. I'm
sorry, just having a little problem here. It's good to be back.
Okay, so today's דף *daf* is כ"ט *chaf tes*, we pick up
at the very bottom of כ"ח עמוד ב' *chaf ches amud bais*.
And I'm sorry, did I, am I off? No, today's דף *daf*
is ל' *lamed*, mistake mistake, revised, today's דף *daf* is ל' *lamed*,
30, we pick up on the bottom of כ"ט עמוד ב' *chaf
tes amud bais*. החשוד להיות מוכר *hachashud l'hiyos mocher*. So we had
started yesterday the discussion about somebody who was suspect, after getting a
fascinating discussion about not being paid for מצוות mitzvos *mitzvos* and all
the potential exceptions for that, then we talk about people that might
be שוחט בכור bechor, *shechting bechor*, selling שביעית shviis *shvi'is*, and that
you cannot purchase from them. And we mentioned two possible reasons, one
because the product itself is אסור בהנאה *asur b'hana'ah*, so you don't
want to accidentally be purchasing from the product that's אסור בהנאה *asur
b'hana'ah*. And the other is you don't want to be indirectly supporting
what they're doing. An interesting potential נפקא מינה *nafka mina* is, you
know, let's say you bought from the person who bought from them,
or let's say you want to, somebody bought from them and discarded
it, could you pick it up and use it? Is the focus
on the object that's coming from their house or is the focus
on not supporting? The simple direct sense seems to be the focus
is on the object, but in other cases the גמרא Gemara *gmara*
is concerned also about you as a purchaser indirectly supporting somebody's illegal
activity, particularly about buying from a גנב *gannav*. But anyway, let's keep
on going. So the next משנה mishna *mishna* at the bottom of
כ"ט עמוד ב' *chaf tes amud bais* says the following. החשוד להיות
מוכר תרומה terumah לשום חולין chullin. *hachashud l'hiyos mocher truma l'shum chulin*.
Somebody is suspect for selling תרומה terumah *truma* under the guise of
חולין chullin *chulin*. So somebody is selling תרומה *truma* and claiming that
it's חולין chullin *chulin*, or at least that there's a reasonable suspicion.
So if you go ahead and eat that and you're a non-כהן
kohen? *kohen*, obviously that's a חייב מיתה בידי שמים *chayav misa bidei
shamayim*. אין לוקחים ממנו *ein lokchim mimenu*, you cannot buy from him,
אפילו מים ומלח *af'ilu mayim u'melach*, דברי רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *divrei
Rabbi Yehuda*, even salt and water. Now here we are finally getting
into beyond just a direct concern that you will improperly benefit from
things that are forbidden. There is a concern about fining this person
and trying to clamp down on this type of behavior. So this
is, this is clearly a larger societal point than not just a
problem about benefiting. At least that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Rabbi
Yehuda* says. One minute, רבי שמעון אומר omer: *Rabbi Shimon omer*, כל
שיש בו זיקת תרומה ומעשרות *kol she'yesh bo zikas truma u'ma'asros*, אין
לוקחים ממנו *ein lokchim mimenu*. Anything that is somewhat connected to תרומה
ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros*, meaning might be
food that have a תרומה ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros* obligation, those you cannot
buy. So we have a very broad definition, not just the classic
things like grains, but nevertheless we do not have a fine outside
of the immediate area of concern.
Yes, this kind of implies that water and salt can be bought
from anybody.
Yeah, they're without הכשר hechsher *hechsher*. As opposed to the קופפאות *kofafos*
that they buy? Okay. Also, there's a famous, you know, מדרש *midrash*
about עשו *Esav*, about עשו *Esav* trying to show how פרום frum
*frum* he was, so he asks יצחק *Yitzchak* how do you take
מעשר maaser *ma'aser* from salt? You know, so those are like the
classic examples of things that don't grow from the ground, so clearly
there's no תרומה ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros* from them. So let's take a
look at the גמרא Gemara, *gmara*. לאתויי מאי *l'asuyei mai*? So what
does the anything that's somehow connected possibly to תרומה ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros*,
what's that including? לאתויי קירבי דגין *l'asuyei kirvei dagin*, even buying fish
guts. Now fish guts, why might that be תרומה ומעשרות *trumos u'ma'asros*?
Why? דמערבי בהו שמן זית *d'm'arvei bo shemen zayis*, because they to,
because it's common to mix some olive oil into them, and olive
oil clearly is חייב בתרומה ומעשרות *chayav b'trumos u'ma'asros*. So even if
a person is only suspect, and it never exactly tells us how
we know he's suspect, presumably is it that people are rumoring, is
it that he was once caught? Right, that's not, that's not being
determined here. But even though he's only suspect, and even though maybe
it's, you know, there's only a small amount of oil that might
be mixed up, maybe you don't even know for sure oil is
mixed up, although it does sound like you know for sure, anyway,
nevertheless, anything that might be connected you don't buy, but something that
definitely is not, like water and salt, you can.
Isn't, isn't תרומה *truma* more expensive than חולין chulin. *chulin*?
No, it's less expensive because it has more restrictions.
Only a כהן kohen
*kohen* can eat it, only when they're טהור *tahor*.
So it's much easier and how would he even get it?
No, he, rather than giving his תרומה *truma* to a כהן *kohen*,
he sells it and he claims it's חולין *chulin*.
Not a merchant.
Right, no, he might be. He's a farmer, he harvests his grain,
but see people suspect that he doesn't give his תרומה ומעשרות *trumos
u'ma'asros*, he rather sells them and claims that they're
חולין *chulin*, causing other people to sin.
Right, he's
causing other people to meddle in others' religious lives.
Well, but we have to protect ourselves as well, you know.
Right,
right. So now the, so let's take a look at the גמרא
Gemara *gmara*. ההוא טבחא דהוה חשוד chashud. לזבוני תרבא דאטמא *hahoo tabcha
d'havay chashud l'zabuni tarba d'atuma*. So talking about כשרות kashrus? *kashrus*, right?
Which is maybe something that we can relate to more. I mean,
this is כשרות kashrus? *kashrus*, but כשרות kashrus, *kashrus* of meat. ההוא
טבחא *hahoo tabcha*, there was a butcher that was suspect of selling
the fat of the
kidneys, ב' מר *b'mar*... under the auspices of דקנתא *d'kanta*, of the
fat of קנתא *kanta*, which is a particular type of fat that
actually is permissible, of one of the, I believe, the intestines. So
therefore basically he said, "Oh yeah, yeah, this is חלב *cheilev*, but
it's the permitted חלב *cheilev*," and there was reasons to suspect that
it wasn't. So קנסיה רבא למיזבני אפילו אמגוזי *Kansyei Rava l'mizvnei afilu
amguzei*. So Rava forbade him, fined him that he could not sell
even nuts. Don't buy anything from this guy, don't even buy nuts.
Okay, so we're fining him for doing this. So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says, like, make up your mind. אמר ליה רב פפא לרבא
*Amar lei Rav Papa l'Rava*, so Rav Papa said to Rava, כמאן
*K'man*? Who you going like? כרבי יהודה *K'Rabbi Yehuda*? You going like
Rabbi Yehuda that fines, that extends it beyond even, you know, beyond
even the object that is problematic? So one minute, אי כרבי יהודה
אפילו מיא ומלחא נמי *Ei k'Rabbi Yehuda afilu maya u'melcha nami*. If
it's Rabbi Yehuda, then you shouldn't let people buy even salt and
water. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ולעולם רבי שמעון *U'l'olam Rabbi
Shimon*. It's really Rabbi Shimon, that it's only things that are connected.
So how are nuts connected? So באיסורא ובאיסורא דגופיה קנסינן ליה *B'issura
u'b'issura d'gufei kansinan lei*. So he does agree that you fine him
in things that are connected. Now that's different. We would have read
Rabbi Shimon that he disagrees with the fine altogether. He just says
objects that might actually be forbidden, don't buy. But here the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*'s reading it, no, no, no, Rabbi Shimon does agree that
you might make a fine, but it has to be somehow related.
So water and salt are not related. So how are nuts related?
So let's take a look. So here's what he used to do.
סתם דרדקי גרירו באמגוזי *Stam dardakei gariru b'amguzei*. Normal kids are drawn
after nuts. When the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* בבא מציעא *Bava Metzia* talks
about, you know, fair business practices, it talks about whether a merchant
is allowed to give out candies and nuts—I mean, I'm saying candies—nuts
to kids, because then it'll bring the kid to the store and
they'll bring their parents to the store. So one says, "No, it's
not fair, you know, I mean, that's not really about the wares,
it's really just about enticing the kids." And the other response is,
"Yeah, but the other merchant can do it as well." So, you
know, are you allowed to do those types of things? So anyway,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* knows that store owners would give out nuts
to get the kids into the store. So normally he would give
out nuts to get the kids in, they would draw after the
nuts. ואזיל ומשבש לבני טבחא *V'azil u'mishabesh l'vnei tapcha*. So what he
would go is he would go and corrupt—it's actually an interesting word
here, משבש *mishabesh*, but it really means he would corrupt—the kids of
the שוחטים *shochtim*, the kids of the butchers. וגרירו להו באמגוזי *V'gariru
lehu b'amguzei*, and he would sort of, you know, seduce them with
nuts. He would go ahead and, you know, give them nuts, the
kids of the butcher, and he'd have them do a little task
for him. What would, what would he have them do? ומייתי ליה
תרבא דאטמא ומזבין ליה במר דקנתא *U'maiti lei tarba d'atma u'mazvin lei
b'mar d'kanta*. He would have said, "Hey, you know, your father's going
to be throwing out all of that חלב *cheilev* anyway, so why
don't you just take it and bring it to me?" So that's
where he would get this fat is he would give nuts to
the kids of the butchers and then he would get it and
then he would sell it. So it might also be גזל gezel,
*gezel* in addition to כשרות kashrus *kashrus* issues. Anyway, so because nuts
were involved in the process, so therefore he fined. So this is
a reframing of Rabbi Shimon that it is not that he doesn't
fine at all, but it has to be a relevant fine. Now,
you know, the point here about כשרות kashrus? *kashrus* and butchers, whatever,
I mean, we all do know, like, you know, what was that
story in Monsey with the guy who was really selling טרפה *treifa*,
whatever. You know, what do you expect people, I mean, obviously we
understand that at a societal level it's important to say if that's
what somebody is doing, we shut down the business. You know, I
mean, or else there's no disincentive for doing it. So then the
only loss of doing it is that I don't, you know, is
that I don't continue to do it, right? There has, so the
idea of making a קנס *knas* makes a lot of sense at
a societal level. What did you want to say, Charlie? I was
going to say... Okay, yes. Or excommunicate the guy.
Let's not discuss.
So that's a good point too, you know, and what, and what
Michael says is a good point that if you remember back in
חולין *Chullin*, right, first of all there's always a question about putting
him in חרם *cherem*. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* in חולין *Chullin* discussed
שוחטים *shochtim* who weren't doing a good enough job and that they
actually were basically prevented from, you know, kicked out of their jobs,
that they were not allowed to continue to be שוחטים *shochtim*. So
it, it is a good question and part of this might be
an issue about חשוד chashud *chashud* as opposed to known to do
it. Right? Of course then you can say if it's חשוד chashud
*chashud* then maybe we're going too far, you know, to prevent people
just because it's at a stage of חשוד chashud *chashud*. So it
is a good question. You have to sort of like pull the
different things together about are we, do we have a consistent policy
in terms of how we deal with these situations? But you're right.
I have not tried to systematize it. I don't, it does not
seem to me that way, but I'm not sure. But you are
correct that in חולין *Chullin* we discuss שוחטים *shochtim* that were suspect
or known to have been doing not, you know, not כשר kosher
*kosher* things and we actually, you know, had different levels of fines
and of removing them from their post. Yes.
That was done in the 20th century. The very first Jew in
Alcoholics Anonymous was a שוחט *shochet* who because he was drunk when
he would try to שחט *shecht*, the rabbis took away his license.
Wow.
Okay, very good. All right, always good for those little fact tidbits,
Charlie. All right, so now, now we continue and you know, this
פרק perek *perek* of בכורות *Bechoros*, you know... for people that were
thinking like, oh my god, we've gone through three מסכתות of קדשים,
Kodshim, you know, and there's still more. This פרק is so relevant
to so many different areas. I mean, we've already dealt with, if
you think about it, you know, we've dealt with the question about
being paid for מצות mitzvos and the questions about I don't know
about you know how rabbis can be paid and how doctors can
be paid, you know, we discussed the whole issue about medical about
legal malpractice and about גרמי garmi and about what defines דין, din,
which has a whole issues about canonization. Anyway, now we turn to
a very central discussion about the issue of חשוד. chashud. So we
start with a narrow case of חשוד chashud by בכור, which is
or by שביעית shviis and whatever, about you know buying from somebody
if you suspect that they're selling you not kosher things. But here
we get to a broader discussion of if somebody is a suspect
in one area, does it mean they can't be trusted in another
area? And this has a lot of very contemporary relevance. So let's
take a look. Right. So let's, yeah, it has come up before.
So let's take a look. החשוד על השביעית אינו חשוד על המעשרות.
Hachashud al hashviis eino chashud al hamaasros. If somebody who is suspect
for you know trading in שביעית shviis product or you know not
following the laws of שמיטה shmita but more specifically trading in them
is not suspect for selling מעשרות maasros as if they were חולין.
Now what type of מעשר maaser, does it mean? So if it's
your normal מעשר, maaser, like you know מעשר עני maaser ani and
מעשר לוי, maaser Levi, so who cares really? I mean, I mean
it's גזל, but it's not like seems to be the context here
where the concern is something that's not kosher or that has restrictions
on how it can be eaten, right, and then that's being presented
as something that has no restrictions. So תוספות Tosafot says and it's
going to be clear from the גמרא Gemara that the context means
מעשר שני. maaser sheni. מעשר שני maaser sheni that has to be
eaten in ירושלים Yerushalayim and he sells it as if it were
חולין and therefore it's going to lead to you transgressing the restrictions
of מעשר שני. maaser sheni. Okay, so somebody who's suspect for שמיטה
shmita is not suspect for מעשר, maaser. for misrepresenting מעשר. ma'aser החשוד
על המעשר אינו חשוד על השביעית. Hachashud al hamaaser eino chashud al
hashviis. And in the same way the reverse. Somebody suspect for selling
מעשר שני maaser sheni as if it were חולין is not suspect
for שמיטה. shmita. החשוד על זה ועל זה הרי זה חשוד על
הטהרות. Hachashud al zeh veal zeh harei zeh chashud al hataharos. If
you're suspect on on on those, then חשוד על הטהרות, chashud al
hataharos, then you are suspect on on טהרות taharos meaning on being
able are do we assume that you handle all of your all
of your food products בטהרה betaharah or not? That is a very
high level, right? As we'll see in the גמרא, gemara that's like
a חבר. chaver. That's considered like this sense of this community of
people that were the חברים chaverim essentially, which was the name, which
was you know extremely scrupulous that they would eat their חולין בטהרה
chullin betaharah and so on. So that's already a very, very high
level. So if once you're suspect on one of these things which
are like real
דאורייתא deoraisa concerns, I think the better read is on either of
them. So it's on a real דאורייתא deoraisa concern then you're certainly
would be suspect of not handling your food בטהרה. betaharah. ויש שהוא
חשוד על הטהרות, Veyeish shehu chashud al hataharos, and
somebody could be suspect on on טהרות, taharos, on not handling their
food בטהרה, betaharah, ואינו חשוד על זה ועל זה, veino chashud al
zeh veal zeh, but you're not suspect for שמיטה shmita and for
מעשרות maasros because obviously one again is a high level of just
you know a פרום קייט frumkeit and the other is a real
דאורייתא deoraisa restriction. זה הכלל, Zeh haklal, this is a general principle,
and this is what's really important.
החשוד על דבר לא דנו ולא מעידו. Hachashud al davar lo dano
velo meido. If somebody is suspect on something you cannot testify to
it, you cannot be a judge about it, tying back to earlier
discussions about being a judge. And the really זה הכלל zeh haklal
you were expecting which the גמרא gemara will say because this זה
הכלל zeh haklal does not summarize what was said before. This is
more about buying from the person and then the משנה mishnah says
you also can't trust them about other things. The real זה הכלל
zeh haklal is החשוד על דבר אחד אינו חשוד על דבר אחר.
hachashud al davar echad eino chashud al davar acher. Right? Just because
you're suspect for one thing doesn't mean that you're suspect for everything.
And I'll talk a little bit more about that in a minute.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. gemara, מאי טעמא? Mai taama?
What's the reason that if you're suspect for שמיטה shmita we don't
assume that that translates into being suspect for other like agricultural מצות?
mitzvos? I mean, aren't they all one category and if you know
if you're not careful about one you won't be careful about the
other? The גמרא Gemara says no, שביעית לא בעי חומה. shviis lo
baei chomah. שביעית shevi'is. doesn't need to be eaten wall, doesn't need
to be eaten in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ומעשר, Umaaser, and but מעשר שני, maaser sheni, here it's
clear what the context, by context what it means, כיון דבעי חומה,
keivan dbaei chomah, since it has to be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
חמיר ליה, chamir leih, you treat it very strictly. Oh my gosh,
it's holy, you bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, right? So therefore you
might treat it with greater sense of severity and just because you're
you're lax about one, you won't be lax about the other. This
is really the גמרא Gemara not talking about the objective reality about
how stringent something is but about the psychological question that in your
mind you can justify or rationalize why you know, eh, this isn't
so important, and you won't necessarily translate into other areas because you
might associate greater sense of of severity with other areas. And that
could very much be not always reflecting the הלכה halacha reality, you
know, and for example, I'll just shift for a minute, you know,
one very important question sadly is the point about if somebody is
suspect for let's say cheating on you know in business, can you
trust their כשרות? kashrus Can you go to their home and trust
their כשרות? kashrus I mean if they violate One מצוה mitzvah where
they would maybe they violate another מצוה? mitzvah? But sadly we know
that the psychology isn't that way; people rationalize violating בין אדם לחבירו;
bein adam l'chavero; that's not really religious, it's only ethical, even though
it's מצוות mitzvos, too, and they treat stuff that's more ritual as
though it was more severe, so they would never think about not
being super מחמיר machmir on כשרות, kashrus, but when it comes to
like business, who cares? So that is a psychology, so the גמרא
Gemara. isn't condoning that, but it's saying that it's acknowledging that reality.
So this principle is again very relevant; somebody basically cheats in business,
you can still trust their כשרות kashrus. in their home. And there
are lessons about how does that lead to other areas as well.
Let's say somebody was known to cheat on his
wife; can you trust his כשרות? kashrus Again the answer is yes,
people compartmentalize and they say that's one type of religious prohibition, this
is a different religious prohibition, okay? And then the only question becomes
what's considered, as the גמרא Gemara. is trying to say, the same
category or not the same category. So if somebody is known, let's
say,
to violate the second day יום טוב, yom tov, do you have
to be concerned that they're violating the first day יום טוב? yom
tov? Or if they violate יום טוב, yom tov, do you have
to be concerned they violate שבת? Shabbos? Do we say that that's
קל וחומר kal v'chomer and people aren't חשוד על דבר קל, chashud
al davar kal, you're not חשוד על דבר חמור, chashud al davar
chamur, or sometimes how do we sort of categorize them together? So
the basic principles in the גמרא, Gemara although you have to figure
out how to define the categories, is that if something is defined
as one category, defined much more, I would say, psychologically than formally,
if it's psychologically people sort of treat it as one unit, then
we would say if you're חשוד chashud on one aspect of the
category then if you're going to do that wrong you're going to
do that wrong. Although we also say חשוד על דבר קל chashud
al davar kal is not חשוד על דבר חמור. chashud al davar
chamur. Okay? So it's also a question about how equivalent they are
in your mind. As we know, people might say יום טוב שני,
yom tov sheini, they'll think differently about it. Now, how nuanced is
that difference? Is יום טוב yom tov and שבת Shabbos a big
enough difference to be קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? So that's a question.
But the basic principle is it has to be one category, at
least psychologically you treat it the same, and we say חשוד על
דבר קל chashud al davar kal is not חשוד על דבר חמור.
chashud al davar chamur. So חז"ל Chazal really understood
the sad psychological reality of people and how we religiously compartmentalize and
can give ourselves license to do one thing wrong and can still
believe and still say, but I'm a פרום frum person, I'm never
going to do that wrong and I wouldn't do that wrong. And
what that means is you don't have to go ahead, on the
one hand you could say, oh, I don't like that, that sounds
like we're condoning that type of mentality. But on the other hand,
what if we didn't say that, it would mean that we couldn't
like eat in half the people's houses, because, so there's a reality
about this and we have to deal with the הלכתית halakhic implications
of that reality.
Maybe even sometimes to be חשוד על דבר חמור chashud al davar
chamur is not חשוד chashud on the same דבר חמור. davar chamur.
Like people don't keep כשר kosher outside but they'll keep כשר kosher
home. So how do you deal with that?
That definitely can become an interesting question, you're right, because normally the
way we define different categories, it still divides on,
meaning while still they're grouped by how you psychologically treat them, they
still are along the lines of הלכתית halakhic units. So שבת Shabbos
is on this side, כשרות Kashrut, is on that side, עריות arayos
is on this side and כשרות is on that side. What you're
saying is what if you took the exact same הלכתית halakhic act,
הלכתית halakhic sin of כשרות, but people make a divide between in
the home and out of the home? That's a very good question
because
there are
a lot of people that
keep כשר kosher at home. You raise a very good point. My
sense is that the הלכה halakha here predominantly is following the psychology
of people and it's a question of the reality. Does actually doing
this mean that there's a basis to suspect them on that?
So yeah, I mean sometimes you'd say people that eat non-כשר out
of the home aren't so careful about it in the
home, but I'd have to think about it more, I'd have to
see if there's material on it. I imagine if you had a
very well-defined phenomenon that this did not bleed into that and that
even though they were the same עבירה aveira but transgressing in this
context never bled in to a leniency in another context that probably
we would say you're not חשוד. chashud That it really does follow
very much the psychology. But I'd have to see if there's material
on that.
To focus, everybody has their own
rationalizations.
I know people that are very particular to have only things with
a הכשר in the house,
like tea, you don't need tea anyway, but to serve somebody else
in your house tea, so then it's a question of respecting other
people.
Right, so that's like Michael's point. If you really can say that
some people when it
comes to things in their own שיקול הדעת. shikul hadaas.
Right, so that's what I was saying. If it's really clear that
that phenomenon is that there's a well-defined phenomenon. people being super מחמיר
*machmir* in their homes regardless of what they do outside, you know,
but if it's a point that, no, amongst the people that eat
non-כשר *kosher* or aren't so careful outside, there's a total range of
how careful they are inside their home as well. So then it's
hard to say that if you know that somebody is in the
category where they're not careful outside, you know, then they might be
anywhere in the range in terms of their home. So you might
have to be concerned. Now, the other however question that I think
you're implicitly asking is, what if you know about this particular individual?
Right. Meaning these rules are telling you your basic guidelines. So let's
say it's true that there are a whole range of people that
aren't כשר *kosher* out of the home, and in the home range
from being very lax to very strict. So if I know that
a random person is not כשר *kosher* out of the home and
he says he keeps כשר *kosher* in the home, I won't be
able to know how כשר *kosher* he really keeps. But if I
know, if I know this particular individual, I know how מחמיר *machmir*
they are in the home, how much does specific knowledge override these
types of things? That, yes, there is definite basis for saying that
that is the case. So you're right, it raises all of those
questions. Yes.
Rabbis use political considerations to deny כשרות *kashrut*
certifications to people.
I had that a few times. In 1990 in Israel, we were
bringing a תורה Torah, *Torah* to Women of the Wall in the
Hyatt. Right. And we had booked well in advance a room there
for a celebration. Right. And the rabbinate told the Hyatt that they
were going to revoke their כשרות *kashrut* certificate if they allowed us
to have our party there. And they didn't allow us. So that's,
I mean, we know that a lot. Right.
There can always be abuse of power.
Which is really wrong. Morally wrong.
Right, absolutely. Now look, there are two stages here. The first משניות
*mishnayot* that say don't buy, we're going to fine them, that's some
rabbinic authority that is sort of, you know, using power and hopefully
in this case in the responsible way. Can
that lead to an abuse of power? Unquestionably. And it's always sad
when כשרות *kashrut* and policy get mixed together. You know, so they
won't give כשרות *kashrut* to a, you know, they won't give כשרות
*kashrut* to a place that, I don't know, that has, you know,
sometimes they'll do crazy things. They won't have a place where boys
and girls, you know, mix or whatever, or certainly right, in some,
whatever it might be. Like they won't play music on the nine
days or something like that.
They won't give a הכשר *hechsher* to something that is open on
Saturday night because of the potential that...
Right. And then the flip of that is though sadly, like I've
spoken to people about this, I am completely shocked that you would
go to a restaurant on סוכות *Sukkot* and they will have a
הכשר *hechsher* and they won't have a כשר *kosher* סוכה *sukkah*.
Oh, all over Manhattan.
And I cannot begin to imagine that because that is directly connected.
You're buying, you're going, you assume it's okay, you're going to go
to the סוכה *sukkah*. How can they continue to give a הכשר
*hechsher* on סוכות *Sukkot* without going and making sure that they have
a כשר *kosher* סוכה *sukkah*? That's ממש *mamash* about eating the food.
So to me that is completely, you know, unimaginable.
Most places that have a הכשר *hechsher* now don't have a סוכה
*sukkah*.
Right. And then, you know, that is ממש *mamash*, as far as
I'm concerned, that is totally, no, if you don't have a סוכה
*sukkah*, that's one thing. Take the food home, you know what the
story is, you're on your own. I'm talking about they have a
סוכה *sukkah*, but it's not כשר *kosher*. They haven't put on enough
סכך *schach*. Oh wow. So that they're totally מכשיל *machshil* people.
Or the restaurant that serves in the restaurant
area and all that on סוכות *Sukkot*. So that's a different question.
That's a question about, you know, maybe right, maybe you're a חולה
*choleh*, maybe you're whatever, you maybe you're הולכי דרכים *holchei drachim*, but
the סוכה *sukkah*, look, that I can make come to terms with,
but the סוכה *sukkah* is basically implicit with the הכשר *hechsher* on
the restaurant is implicitly telling people it's a כשר *kosher* סוכה *sukkah*.
Anyway, look, there are other issues as well. You know, when the
whole thing came up last year, now you've got me on a
whole digression, but when the whole thing came up last year, or
not last year, a few years ago, you know, about the whole
issue
about ethics and כשרות *kashrut* and so on, and all these כשרות
*kashrut* places say, oh, we're just about כשר *kosher*, we're not about,
you know, ethics. If it's just about כשר *kosher*, then why do
you use policy in other places to determine? It's a question of
which policies you're using. And thankfully that's changed a little. There is,
it is true that the Star-K, I think it's the Star-K, has
always consistently said, we're not about any policy issues, it's, I don't
care what else you're doing, we're just about the כשרות *kashrut*. Okay.
Even with that, I would question the restaurants on the סוכה *sukkah*
issue because that I think is directly about eating the food. Anyway,
that's all digression. The point is, is that yes, is it important
that can saying, you know, you can't trust, you can't trust, you
should buy from this store, you can't buy from this store. On
the one hand, power used responsibly is what we need, is about,
you know, leadership and is about helping society and so on. But
the problem is, is that it can be used irresponsibly and there
could be an abuse of power and that's unquestionably that that happens,
you know, in the field of כשרות *kashrut*. But the question is,
moving back to this, is this is not necessarily even about the
rabbinic authority. This is about me as an individual. I know this
person isn't careful about this, isn't careful about שביעית shevi'is *sheviit*, can
I trust
their
מעשר ma'aser *maaser*? even if the עבירה aveira, I know this person
does is much more serious than a different עבירה, but if in
their mind they compartmentalize and one doesn't translate into the other, I
can trust them on something even if they transgress very serious things.
I can trust them on something else if for them they treat
it as a different matter. So let's keep on going.
It's a global world though, because you said it might be subject
to individual circumstances.
Yeah, that's right, just to be there.
Do you question them and you trust their response then?
Yeah, like with all cases, like anytime you're eating in somebody's home,
you know, you... I mean, sometimes you don't even have to question
them. Sometimes there's a general, you know, general thing you assume that
people eat kosher in their home. So even though you know that
this person has done certain other terrible things, doesn't necessarily mean that
you have to start saying, I can't trust their כשרות. Okay. So
let's take... I mean, that's the irony, right? That people are very,
very פרום frum about their כשרות and they could be very not
פרום Frum about much more serious things. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: החשוד על המעשר hachashud al hama'aser and the
same is reversed, if you're suspect by מעשר ma'aser, you're not suspect
by שביעית. shevi'is. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? מעשר אית
ליה פדיון ma'aser is lei pidyon because in your mind making מעשר
ma'aser. you can rationalize it, you can redeem מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni,
so therefore it's not so חמור. chamur. שביעית כיון דקמיתסר לה, shevi'is
kivan dekamissar lah, שביעית shevi'is.
is always forbidden, you know, to use in certain ways and after
a certain period of time, therefore it can never be redeemed, in
your mind it's more strict. ולית ליה פדיון v'lais lei pidyon and
it doesn't have redemption. חמירא ליה, chamira lei, you treat it as
strict, and therefore if you allow yourself to be lenient on מעשר,
ma'aser. you won't necessarily allow yourself to be lenient on שביעית. shevi'is.
החשוד על זה ועל זה, hachashud al zeh v'al zeh, if you're
suspect on... it could mean both of them, but I think it
should be understood either of them, then you are suspect on
טהרות. taharos. כיון דחשיד אדאורייתא כל שכן אדרבנן. keivan d'chashid ad'oraisa kol
shekein ad'rabbanan. If you're suspect on a דאורייתא d'oraisa certainly on a
דרבנן d'rabbanan and this is again assumed to be because they are
seen to be related categories, although logically they're not. One is agricultural
מצוה, mitzvah, one is טהרות, taharos, but part of the point about
eating everything בטהרה b'taharah is because of concern of issues like תרומה
and so on. So these are somehow seen as psychologically in the
same category and if you're concerned about the more strict... and if
you're suspect about the more strict, you're suspect on the more lenient.
ויש שחשוד על טהרות. v'yeish shehachashud al taharos. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama,
and if you're suspect on טהרות taharos you're not suspect on שביעית.
shevi'is. Why? נהי דאדרבנן חשיד אדאורייתא לא חשיד. nehi d'adrabbanan chashid ad'oraisa
lo chashid. True you might violate
דרבנן d'rabbanan but a דאורייתא d'oraisa
you won't. רמינהי, reminhi, I'm asking on this, we have a ברייתא
Baraisa that says otherwise. נאמן על הטהרות נאמן על השביעית. ne'eman al
hataharos ne'eman al hashevi'is. If you're trusted on טהרות taharos then you're
trusted on שביעית. shevi'is החשוד חשוד. hachashud chashud. It sounds like if
you're suspect for טהרות taharos for not handling your חולין בטהרה chullin
b'taharah you're suspect for שביעית. shevi'is. One minute, so how do you
deal with that? So אמר רבי אילא, amar Rabbi Ila, מתניתין כשהיו
נוהגין חולין בטהרה. masnisin k'shehayu nohagin chullin b'taharah. You're right, generally if
you're suspect for טהרות taharos you are suspect for שביעית shevi'is even
though it's קל kal and חמור, chamur, you would not... you would
not distinguish them and therefore when you're suspect for one, you're suspect
for the next. So what does our משנה mishnah mean? So our
משנה mishnah says notice the phrasing of our משנה mishnah is funny.
ויש שהוא חשוד. v'yeish shehu chashud. There is a case, right? You
could read it as there... when people are suspect on one they're
not, but maybe you read the משנה mishnah as there are sometimes
when somebody is suspect on טהרות taharos and not suspect on שביעית.
shevi'is What would be that case? That you have peeked into the
guy's home and you see that he's very careful on שביעית shevi'is
and he's very careful on מעשר. ma'aser So therefore even though you
know in his home... he's not doing it for appearance's sake, right?
He's doing it because he obviously... unless he thinks that people might
be peeking into his home! But we'll assume he's not doing it
for appearance's sake. So therefore, right, so therefore even though he's suspect
on טהרות taharos you can still trust him on שביעית shevi'is and
מעשר. ma'aser, Why? Not as a general rule, but if you peek
into his home and see that he's being careful, because it is
possible for people to distinguish. So here's an interesting middle category, right?
The point is like this: if we would say people never distinguish
between the two, let's say somebody is suspect on מעשר ma'aser and
then you peek in his home and you see he's being careful
about מעשר, ma'aser that presumably is not enough evidence to counteract that,
okay? Maybe once he's suspect there needs to be much more substantial
evidence, maybe not one time, maybe only occasionally he's suspect and so
on. So peeking in the home doesn't help to counteract the general
suspicion. But because it's theoretically possible that some people distinguish... not everybody
distinguishes, but some people distinguish in their mind between טהרות taharos on
the one side and מעשר ma'aser and שביעית shevi'is on the other,
then when we... when we... when we can actually sort of see
that they're being careful on מעשר ma'aser, and שביעית shevi'is and we
see they're doing it in private and they're not doing it for
appearances, that gives us a basis now for distinguishing between those two
categories. So some interesting middle category where we say A means that
we are going to assume B, but it's not always the case
and therefore if we have evidence to the contrary, we will distinguish
between those categories.
Yes. Where it says suspect regarding דרבנן d'rabbanan but not a דאורייתא,
d'oraisa, this... the context would seem to imply that they're accepting that
שביעית shevi'is is דרבנן d'rabbanan at that time.
No, that שביעית shevi'it is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. Meaning טהרות, taharos, even חולין
בטהרה chullin b'taharah is דרבנן d'rabbanan and שביעית shevi'it and מעשר ma'aser.
is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. That's
the
דאורייתא. d'oraisa.
This seems backwards then.
Why is it backwards? It seems, yeah, it says if you are
חשוד chashud on שמיטה shemittah and מעשר, ma'aser you're חשוד chashud on
טהרות. taharot.
It says, okay, but it says if you're suspect regarding a דרבנן,
de-rabbanan, you're not suspect regarding a דאורייתא.
de-oraita.
Yes. The משנה mishnah said if you're suspect on טהרות, taharot, you're
not suspect on שמיטה. shemittah. Okay, okay. Okay? Why? Because טהרות taharot
is דרבנן de-rabbanan and שמיטה shemittah is a דאורייתא. de-oraita. Fine. So
anyway, so the first answer is that really, even though it's קל
וחומר, kal ve-chomer, it is one category in your mind, but it's
potentially two, and if we actually
have seen, have evidence, then we will say that one does not
lead to the other. Okay, that's what רבי אילעא's Rabbi Ila'i answer
is.
רבי ינאי ורבי ישמעאל אומר, Rabbi Yannai ve-Rabbi Ishmael omer, כגון דהוה
חשוד דתרוייהו, k'gon de-havat chashud de-taryehu, so he says no, no, no.
The משנה mishnah is פשט. peshat. If you're חשוד chashud on טהרות,
taharot, you're not חשוד chashud on שמיטה shemittah and מעשר. ma'aser טהרות
taharot is lenient, שמיטה shemittah and מעשר ma'aser is weighty. טהרות taharot
is דרבנן, de-rabbanan, it's not even דרבנן, de-rabbanan, whatever, שמיטה shemittah and
מעשר ma'aser is דאורייתא. de-oraita. So therefore if you do a minor
violation, it doesn't mean you're going to do a heavier one. So
what's פשט peshat in the משנה mishnah that says only if you're
trusted on טהרות, taharot, you're trusted on שמיטה? shemittah? The ברייתא beraita
rather. So he says like
this: כגון דהוה חשוד דתרוייהו, k'gon de-havat chashud de-taryehu, or על תרוייהו.
al taryehu. You were חשוד chashud for both of them. You were
known to violate both מעשר ma'aser and
טהרות. taharot. ואתא קמי רבנן וקבילי דתרוייהו, ve-ata kamei rabbanan ve-kabbilei de-taryehu,
he came in front of the rabbis and he said 'I'm doing
תשובה, teshuvah, I accept from here on in to be very, very
strict, both on שמיטה shemittah and on טהרות.' taharot. והדר איחשד דחד
מנייהו, ve-hadar ichshad de-chad minaihu, and then we see this backsliding, then
we see oh, he's messing up now again and he's not being
good about טהרות. taharot. So in that case, דאמרינן מיגו דאיחשד אהא
חשנינן נמי אדך. d-amrinan migo de-ichshad ahai chashinan nami adach.
Since there is backsliding on one, there was probably backsliding on the
other. So when does the משנה mishnah, say if you're trusted for
טהרות taharot you're trusted for שמיטה shemittah and they're a unit? That's
when you had violated both and then you were doing תשובה teshuvah
and therefore now you have to sustain the right level for both
of them, and if you slip on one then you'll start being
suspect for the
other again. It's a very narrow אוקימתא okimta of that, it does
not sound like that was פשט, peshat, but nevertheless it's a way
of dealing with this contradiction. But
so as a general rule according to the second answer, it keeps
the פשט peshat of the משנה, mishnah and as a general rule
if you're חשוד chashud on טהרות, taharot, you're not חשוד chashud on
שמיטה shemittah and מעשר ma'aser because טהרות taharot is a דרבנן de-rabbanan
and שמיטה shemittah and מעשר ma'aser, is a דאורייתא. de-oraita. It only
one will only lead to the other if they came as a
package and there was violation and backsliding and so on.
So the ברייתא's beraita saying when you are חשוד chashud on one
you're חשוד Chashud on the other is when you it's a case
of backsliding.
Right. Okay, so now we go on. But the basic principle again
is, as you see, that if things can be distinguished as different
categories, we don't translate them. If they're sort of treated as one
category we do, will lenient lead to the we distinguish between lenient
and more severe, also depends to some degree on psychology. Sometimes we
will say lenient won't lead to severe, sometimes we'll say in your
mind it's all one anyway. So let's keep on going. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
Where are we?
Okay, רבי ינאי ורבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yannai ve-Rabbi Ishmael, oh we just
read that. אמר רבי אבא בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן, amar
Rabbi Abba bar Bar Hana amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו דברי רבי עקיבא
סתימאה. zu divrei Rabbi Akiva stima'ah. This משנה mishna is רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, he is the author of this סתם משנה. stam mishnah.
Not exactly clear how we know that, רש"י Rashi just says because
so many, many סתם משניות stam mishnayot are רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
אבל, aval, well yeah, רש"י Rashi deals with that, maybe רבי מאיר
אליבא דרבי עקיבא. Rabbi Meir aliba de-Rabbi Akiva. אבל חכמים אומרים, aval
chachamim omrim, the Sages say, חשוד על שביעית חשוד על מעשר, chashud
al shevi'it chashud al ma'aser, that we do translate from one to
the other. And now that's going to be a question. Are they
arguing just about the particular application, or are they arguing about the
whole principle that we distinguish between categories? So let's take a look.
מאן חכמים, man chachamim, who are the חכמים? chachamim? רבי יהודה. Rabbi
Yehuda, It's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Why? דבאתריה דרבי יהודה שביעית חמירא
להו. de-v'atria de-Rabbi Yehuda shevi'it chamira le-hu. So this interpretation means it's
only arguing about the detail, that in the place of רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda שביעית shevi'it is very strict. So anybody who would violate
שביעית shevi'it would certainly be suspect about violating מעשר ma'aser as well.
So it's just a question about one application. In principle we don't
say if you're suspect for A you're suspect for B, but here
because שביעית's shvi'is. so weighty, it does lead to being suspect in
other areas. How do we know שביעית shvi'is was so weighty in
his place? דההוא דהוה קרי ליה לחבריה דיירא בר דיירא. de-hahu de-havat
kari lei le-chavrei dayara bar dayara. Apparently in רבי יהודה's place somebody
used to call his neighbor,
his friend, not such a friend, his enemy anyway, you convert the
son of a convert, which was apparently an
insult, which raises very serious questions in general about attitudes towards converts
and ואהבתם את הגר ve-ahavtem et ha-ger etc. Anyway, he whether it
was actually factually the case or not, it sounds like it might
have actually been factually the case, he said this as a way
of putting the other guy down. ואמר ליה, ve-amar lei, so the
person said back to him, תיתי לי, taysi li, well at least
at least it's good for me דלא אכלי דשביעית כוותך, d'lo achli
de'shviis kevaseich, at least I'm not as bad as you, I don't
eat שמיטה shemittah like you do. So, and the fact that he
used that as an insult is so fascinating what we're learning from
it, shows how terrible that sin was considered. You know, well, at
least I don't eat חזיר, chazir, so at least I don't eat
שמיטה, shemittah, so clearly that indicates that the sin was very strict,
and therefore if you're suspect for one, you're suspect for the other.
So that's just a local debate about that particular application. איכא דאמרי,
ika d'amri, others say, אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו דברי רבי עקיבא
סתימאה, zu divrei Rabbi Akiva stima'ah, this משנה is סתם משנה stam
mishna of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, אבל חכמים אומרים, aval chachamim omrim,
the sages say, חשוד על המעשר חשוד על השביעית, chashud al hama'aser
chashud al hashvi'is, if you're חשוד Chashud for מעשר, ma'aser, you're חשוד
Chashud for שביעית. shvi'is, Now, as opposed to before, we said for
שביעית you're חשוד Chashud for מעשר ma'aser, because of the particular weight
of שמיטה. shemittah. Here we're saying if you're suspect for מעשר, you're
suspect for שמיטה. shvi'is. ומאן חכמים, uman chachamim, who are the חכמים?
chachamim? רבי מאיר היא, Rabbi Meir hi, דאמר חשוד לדבר אחד הוי
חשוד לכל התורה כולה. d'amar chashud l'davar echad havi chashud l'chol hatorah
kullah. And here is the argument in principle, and now you could
see why thank God for the sages that at least accept the
psychological reality of our own, you know, contradictory and compartmentalized mind. Because
if you're רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who says, you know, if somebody's
willing to violate a דאורייתא, d'oraisa, then they don't hold by the
system, and then maybe they violate everything else. So therefore,
as soon as you're suspect for violating one thing, we have to,
we can't trust you at all in terms of your religiosity, and
we have to suspect you for everything. Okay, so that would obviously
lead to some pretty profound implications at a societal level. So, now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, רבי יונה ורבי ירמיה תלמידי דרבי
זירא, Rabbi Yonah v'Rabbi Yirmiyah talmidei d'Rabbi Zeira, ואמרי לה רבי יונה
ורבי זירא, v'amri lah Rabbi Yonah v'Rabbi Zeira, so רבי יונה Rabbi
Yonah and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah were the students of רבי זירא,
Rabbi Zeira, ואמרי לה רבי יונה ורבי זירא תלמידי דרבי יוחנן, v'amri
lah Rabbi Yonah v'Rabbi Zeira talmidei d'Rabbi Yochanan, and some say רבי
יונה Rabbi Yonah and רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira were the students of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, and this is what they said, not just
that they were the students, but this is what they said. חד
אמר אבל חכמים אומרים חשוד על השביעית. chad amar aval chachamim omrim
chashud al hashvi'is. Now we're just going to repeat this. One of
them said that yes, that's a סתם משנה, stam mishna, but the
sages say suspect for שביעית, חשוד על המעשר, chashud al hama'aser, ומאן
חכמים רבי יהודה, uman chachamim Rabbi Yehuda, and that's the רבי יהודה
that for him they knew that in his place שמיטה shemittah was
very weighty. וחד אמר, v'chad amar, and the other says, חשוד על
המעשר חשוד על השביעית. chashud al hama'aser chashud al hashvi'is. No, if
you're suspect for מעשר, you're suspect for שמיטה. shvi'is. ומאן חכמים רבי
מאיר, uman chachamim Rabbi Meir, and it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. And
now we're going to see where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if
you're suspect for one thing, you're suspect for everything. דתניא, d'tanya, we
learned in a ברייתא, braisa, עם הארץ שקיבל עליו דברי חבירות. am
ha'aretz shekibel alav divrei chaveirus. If an
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, one of the people of the land, right,
accepted upon himself to act as a חבר. chaver. A חבר chaver
again is, you know, often there's this whole question, and we're actually
going to see in a minute or later in today's דף, that
the community of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim is not the same as
the community of חברים. chaverim. חברים chaverim was very much about people
that were very careful about טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah and eating their
חולין בטהרה, chullin b'taharah,
and you know, again, I often think that this sort of, it's
also reflected, you know, in the stories in the Gospels where Jesus,
you know, is eating with the prostitutes and the tax collectors and
so on. I mean, I'm not the one who says this, other
people have recognized this, that the whole idea of like who you
eat or you're eating with and your eating groups was treated extremely
seriously around issues of purity, particularly in the בית שני Bayis Sheini
time, and it continued after the בית שני. Bayis Sheini. So the
whole idea of eating חולין בטהרה, chullin b'taharah, you know, which is
seen as connected to this institution called חבר chaver and חבירות, chaveirus,
חבירות, chaveirus, anyway, so that is what's being referred to. And you
know, and often there's an assumption that that overlaps with the sense
of being like part of the rabbinic and תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim
class and being scrupulous about מצוות, mitzvos. but it is a very
different type of, but even if there's a lot of overlap, conceptually
it's different. It's about this sort of community that's very careful about
תרומה ומעשר terumah u'ma'aser and about eating בטהרה. b'taharah. So let's say
you are a person that wants to become now a חבר. chaver.
ונחשד לדבר אחד, v'nechshad l'davar echad, so
if once you are suspected for one thing, נחשד לכל התורה כולה,
nechshad l'chol hatorah kullah, you're suspect for everything. דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
Rabbi Meir. So you were accepted as a חבר, chaver, you were
accepted into our society, that maybe is the word I was looking
for, like an eating society, right, like these, so you were accepted
into our society and now we see that there's something you're not
doing right. So that's it, we have to suspect you're doing everything
wrong. וחכמים אומרים אינו נחשד אלא לאותו דבר בלבד. v'chachamim omrim eino
nechshad ella l'oso davar bilvad. No, you're only suspect for the one
thing that you violated. Now again, what's interesting is that although חבירות
chaveirus is about this eating society and about חולין בטהרה, chullin b'taharah,
it is being translated here more generally, right? And it is being
sort of, and this happens in the גמרא, Gemara that sort of
the institution of חבר chaver somehow gets sort of the same way
the rabbis become פרושים, perushim, Pharisees, you know, and also here too,
right, it's sort of like taking a second temple institution and sort
of seeing it as continuous. I mean, it might be to some
degree related, but anyway, so here too there's an assumption that the
sense of this community of חבירות chaveirus is essentially the community of
religious rabbinic Jews that are careful about מצוות. Mitzvot, So this discussion
about when do you get kicked out of this community is translated
into this question of if you are generally just a Jew who
is suspect for violating one thing. ...saying, then in general we're just
going to suspect you for everything. Okay, so that's how רבי מאיר's
Rabbi Meir position is translated more broadly than just the aspect of
חברות, Chaveirut, חברות. Chaveirut. So that's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now we
go on and you see it's about sort of being accepted and
then being in or out of the group. הגר שקיבל עליו, Hager
shekibel alav, let's just read a little bit more. הגר שקיבל עליו
דברי תורה, Hager shekibel alav divrei Torah, now a גר Ger accepted,
it's an interesting whole phrase. It's not גר שהתגייר, Ger shehitgayer, it's
a גר Ger that accepted to do the מצוות, Mitzvot, which is
part of what גרות Gerut is about. אפילו נחשד לדבר אחד הרי
הוא חשוד לכל התורה כולה. Afilu nechshad ledavar echad harei hu chashud
lechol haTorah kullah. Now that sounds, I'm sorry, I skipped the חכמים.
Chachamim. והחכמים אומרים, Vehachachamim omrim, oh no I did read it, אין
נחשד לדבר אחד. Ein nechshad ledavar echad. Now הגר שקיבל עליו דברי
תורה אפילו נחשד לדבר אחד הרי הוא חשוד לכל התורה כולה. Hager
shekibel alav divrei Torah afilu nechshad ledavar echad harei hu chashud lechol
haTorah kullah. Well that's not clear. Is this once more רבי מאיר?
Rabbi Meir? So and then also it's a little bit disturbing, right?
Why just a גר? Ger? Like didn't רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say?
So maybe it is, maybe רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if you
started off in the community of פרום Frum Jews, then just because
you're suspect for one thing we're not going to suspect you for
everything. But if you're coming from the outside, what does it mean
to come from the outside? To come from being an עם הארץ
Am Ha'aretz or to come from being a non-Jew, then it's much
harder to internalize those things and therefore we are suspect that one
thing interprets other things. That would be a very consistent way of
reading רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, but it's not the way the גמרא
Gemara reads רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. The גמרא Gemara reads רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir that he's making a general statement even for people that
were born into the community of פרום frum, Jews, that once you're
suspect for one you're suspect for another. So it raises the question
about do you read this גר Ger thing, which is troubling enough
as it is, do you read it only in רבי מאיר? Rabbi
Meir? And then the question is then why is he limiting himself
to גר? Ger? Or do you read it in the חכמים? Chachamim?
And then it becomes even more troubling because then it means that
we have more suspect of גרים Gerim than we are of normal
Jews. So let me just read it and talk about another גרסא
Girsa and then I'll take some questions. So this sounds like this
is talking about even the חכמים Chachamim and it says that once
he's suspect for one he's suspect for everything and nevertheless הרי הוא
כישראל מומר, Harei hu k'Yisrael mumar, it doesn't mean he's not a
Jew. He's like a Jew who is a rebellious Jew who you
can't assume is doing the מצוות, mitzvos. but nevertheless he doesn't risk
his Jewish status. ונפקא מינה, Venafka mina, the implications of there is,
דקידש קידושיו קידושין. Dekiddesh kiddushav kiddushin. If he were to marry a
woman, it would be a good קידושין. Kiddushin. We're not saying he's
not a Jew, we're not saying his acts are not Halachically binding
as a Jew. What we're saying is that you can't necessarily trust
him in terms of areas of כשרות, שבת, Shabbat, and so on.
Now this is very troubling if it's not within רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. If it's in רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir then fine, he says
it about Jews then all Jews, you know, same thing about גרים,
Gerim, but then why is he mentioning specifically גר? Ger? Which
is a good reason to think that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir himself
really might not be talking about all Jews, he might just be
talking about people that come from the outside. But if it's in
the חכמים, Chachamim, then it's very problematic. Do we actually say this?
That with every single גר Ger in the community, as soon as
they, you know, if they do one thing wrong, they're more suspect
than the Jews? So if you take a look, first of all
there's a very important different גרסא Girsa on the side, which is
the ד Dalet here in the שיטה מקובצת. Shita Mekubetzet. It's very
small print, I don't know if you can see it, but he
says like this: ובגר שקיבל עליו דברי תורה ונחשד לדבר אחד ואפילו
חשוד לכל התורה כולה הרי הוא כישראל לכל דבריו. Uv'ger shekibel alav
divrei Torah venechshad ledavar echad va'afilu chashud lechol haTorah kullah harei hu
k'Yisrael lechol devarav.
So it's actually that the whole point of the statement is to
say that even when a גר Ger whether he's חשוד Chashud for
one thing or for anything, he doesn't risk his Jewish status, he
doesn't lose his Jewish status. It changes the גרסא. Girsa. It's not
saying if you're חשוד Chashud. for one thing you're חשוד Chashud for
everything and you don't lose your Jewish status. It says whether you're
חשוד Chashud for one thing, whether you're חשוד for everything, even if
you violate every single מצוה Mitzvah in the תורה, Torah once you
convert you remain a Jew.
Now that rolls into a סוגיא. Sugya.
No it isn't, because it's talking about the implications of being חשוד.
And being חשוד as a חבר Chaver means you get kicked out
of the club. Being חשוד as a גר Ger doesn't mean you
get kicked out of the club. No, that's the point.
But that's obvious, no?
No it isn't. It has to be said and it isn't obvious.
And you would be very interested to find out, sadly, some פסקים
Psakim that are coming out nowadays of people that say, oh well
if you stopped being fully observant after your גירות, Geirut, now we're
going to question the whole גירות Geirut retroactively, which is basically exactly
against this גמרא. Gemara So that's first of all a very important
thing, that then it's making a statement that not that we're more
חושד Choshed a גר, Ger, but that the implications is by a
חבר Chaver is that you get kicked out of the club, by
a גר, Ger, גירות Geirut it doesn't risk the Jewish status. I
will say the possible other reading and then I will take your
question. It is a possible reading and it is unfortunate that there
is, I mean you know there are two general approaches towards גרים
Gerim in the גמרא. Gemara You
know, one is extremely positive and the other is very suspicious. And
the suspicious approach, you know, speaks about the concern about backsliding. So
is it possible that this is with our גרסא Girsa it reflects
that concern and more suspects גרים Gerim than other people if once
they're suspect for one they're suspect for another? That is a possible
read of this גמרא Gemara and it does reflect that attitude that
exists among חז"ל Chazal that is always suspicious of גרים Gerim backsliding.
Of course it raises very serious questions in terms of the basic
מצוה Mitzvah of ואהבתם את הגר Va'ahavtem et hager and so
on if they're always...
So it says הגר
שקיבל עליו דברי תורה. hager shekibal alav divrei Torah. There is a
class of גרים gerim who did not accept the entire Torah, which
is a גר קטן. ger katan.
Yes, that's an interesting point and maybe that also if you read
this that it's like we're going to suspect you then more than
maybe again I don't know if it was intended to make that
distinction. You're being very מדייק medayek like the גמרא Gemara is מדייק.
medayek. Why do you have to say that? I mean I guess.
But that's the other, that's the other question. Is there such a
thing as a גר ger
who...
Right. So no, I mean look, that okay that gets into a
much larger conversation about what's the what is the scope and the
implications
of of קבלת מצוות kabbalas mitzvos and so on. But I will
say in terms of your first read and I don't know if
this was intended that you could be correct that somebody that was
converted as a minor and grew up
more with with Jewish observance, if the read of this is not
what the שיטה מקובצת Shittah Mekubetzet says but the read in our
גמרא Gemara then the suspicion would be a lot less than somebody
who as an
adult had a whole other entrenched in a whole other series of
practices. But it is a it is definitely a very challenging גמרא
Gemara from that perspective. I certainly prefer the reading of the שיטה
מקובצת. Shittah Mekubetzet.
Just one quick question, חמשה אינן נחשב אלא באותו דבר בלבד. Chamishah
einan nechshav ella be'oso davar bilvad.
Does
that mean and maybe other things that are like very specific?
Yeah, yeah, you have to define what אותו דבר oso davar is,
which is what we've been talking about. Okay. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
הבא לקבל דברי חברות haba lekabbel divrei chavairus and here again you
want to be accepted into, you want to accept upon yourself this
fellowship, this what did I call before the society of חברות, chavairus,
you want to be part of this group and then as a
result you're going to be trusted for תרומות ומעשרות וטהרות trumos umasros
vetaheros once you're part of this group. So חוץ מדבר אחד chutz
midavar echad but you say but there's one thing I don't want
to I do just one thing I can't do right now. So
then אין מקבלין אותו, ein mekabelin oso, you don't accept him in
the group. He has to accept all of the rules or we
don't want you. או עובד כוכבים שבא לקבל דברי תורה o oved
kochavim sheba lekabbel divrei Torah חוץ מדבר אחד. chutz midavar echad. Now
let's say a non-Jew would want, wants to accept, again interesting how
it speaks about coming to convert, framing it as accepting the words
of תורה because this is about the question of whether your observance
will be at the at the ideal standard. So before it was
a question about when when you did accept and now there was
backsliding, does that lead to broader suspicion? Here the question is from
the outset are we prepared to accept when it is not at
the ideal standard? So here it says אין מקבלין אותו, ein mekabelin
oso, you do not accept him. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר Rabbi
Yossi BeRabbi Yehuda omer אפילו דקדוק אחד מדברי סופרים, afilu dikduk echad
midivrei sofrim, even if he does not accept one tiny little tittle
of law of the sages. Now this as you can imagine, what,
initially? Well,
right, as you can imagine this גמרא right is very important how
you interpret this גמרא in the context of what is the scope
of קבלת מצוות. kabbalas mitzvos. You could easily interpret this גמרא and
say that it's very clear from this גמרא that you have to
accept and you have to be able to perform every single מצוה
mitzvah to the utmost and if you're even lenient in one area
or not performing one area at the moment that you're converting it's
not a valid conversion. It is possible to read it that way.
However, a number of ראשונים, Rishonim, most ראשונים Rishonim don't really directly
engage this גמרא all together and number one, and those that do
actually read carefully make the point and רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe
Feinstein points this out in a תשובה tshuvah although he only re-phrases
it as a possibility but I really think that this is overwhelmingly
the way the ראשונים Rishonim understood this, that this is just a
לכתחילה lechatchila point. This is about whether we should make the decision
to accept somebody or not. This is not whether the conversion will
be good. Okay? The conversion will be good is a סוגיא ביבמות
sugya b'Yevamos about what constitutes קבלת מצוות. kabbalas mitzvos. Okay? And you
know and there there are very important questions that can be raised
like the important question that the אבני נזר Avnei Nezer raises if
he distinguishes between עול מצוות ol mitzvos and קיום מצוות. kiyom mitzvos.
He says it's one thing to accept that it's your responsibility to
do all the מצוות. mitzvos? That doesn't mean that necessarily you actually
are at the stage where you're doing everything you're responsible to do
but you do acknowledge and accept that as your what?
There's no way you can learn everything before.
Right. And points out exactly that the גמרא speaks about just teaching
sort of general מקצת מצות קלות מקצת מצות חמורות. miktzas mitzvos kalos
miktzas mitzvos chamoros. So obviously, but there you could finesse then and
say okay we're not saying that he has to know everything but
he we have to basically assume that as soon as he learns
something he's going to observe it as opposed to somebody that says
I'm not yet ready to observe I know what I'm supposed to
do I'm not yet ready to, can that be a קבלת מצוות
kabbalas mitzvos if you're not fully ready to perform all of them?
Anyway, but that's a discussion in יבמות.
Yevamos. Is there a distinction in other areas between המקבל hamikabbel and
actually doing מצוות?
I don't know. Anyway, that's a discussion in יבמות. Yevamos. This גמרא
speaks about מקבלין אותו mekabelin oso which is more about the decision
whether it's appropriate to accept the person not whether that actually
will not actually whether it
it it's the definition of the act of קבלת מצוות. kabbalas mitzvos.
But that being said... said, you know, that רב משה *Rav Moshe*
discusses it, רב קוק *Rav Kook* discusses, a lot of אחרונים *achronim*.
There are some אחרונים *achronim*, I think the ראשונים *rishonim* are very
clearly against it, there are some אחרונים *achronim* that read this גמרא
*Gemara* and that say that even somebody that's not prepared to perform
even one thing, the גירות *geirus* בדיעבד *bedieved* is חל *chal*, not
just it's a לכתחילה *l'chatchila* question, there are some אחרונים *achronim* that
read the גמרא *Gemara* this way.
But they take away, they the case that happened in Israel, you
know, a woman who was wearing pants.
I know that case.
And they said she doesn't need a גט *get* because she's never
was really Jewish anyway.
Right, I know that, I know. Basically they took her up. Right,
right. No, I read that story. The story was was that a
woman actually
she was converted, she was living in Israel, her children... right, right,
and
she needed a גט *get* and the בית דין *beis din* started
investigating and she wore pants and didn't cover her...
right, I remember that.
And they said you really don't need a גט *get*.
Right, and the funny thing about that is, and what makes that
even more, you know, sort of objectionable.
Frightening, they took away all her conversions. That was the case that
started it.
And what makes that, you know, even more intoll-, you know, just
so profoundly objectionable is that that's when the observance changed after the
גירות *geirus*. And there the גמרא *Gemara* directly discusses that. The גמרא
*Gemara* says that a גר ger: *ger* could get out of the
מקוה *mikvah* and start worshipping עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* and they're still
a Jew. So the only question is, right, the state even if
you have an extremely high standard of קבלת מצוות *kabbalas mitzvos*, it's
only for the moment of the act of conversion. And the גמרא
*Gemara* is very clear that violation afterwards does not make us reassess
the act of conversion. What the בית דין *beis din* is doing
now in Israel is they are not only creating an extremely high
standard but they're saying that behavior later makes us go back and
suspect what the state of mind was at the time.
What they say is if the גמרא *Gemara* says she performs Judaism.
Before...
well after...
you have to
control... My rabbi heard from רב ליכטנשטיין *Rav Lichtenstein* that if a
בית דין *beis din* hears from a woman that she's not going
to cover her hair, she's going to sing in front of men,
and she's going to wear pants, that she should still convert her.
Right. Right. So that raises an important question, you're right, and it
raises, you know, so then it raises the question, even if I
read this גמרא *Gemara* as חוץ מדבר אחד *chutz midavar echad*, you
know, as a לכתחילה *l'chatchila*,
so then it would still say okay, so maybe I won't say
בדיעבד *bedieved* but לכתחילה *l'chatchila* you shouldn't convert anybody that's not prepared
to do everything. So then it gets into a larger discussion which
again through the evidence of many many תשובות *teshuvos* over hundreds of
years and some want to point to the גמרא *Gemara* for example,
the obviously contrary גמרא *Gemara* to this which is important and we
this is we're gonna have to move on, is the גמרא *Gemara*
about הלל *Hillel* and the person that comes to הלל *Hillel* and
says, teach me the תורה כולה *Torah kula* על מנת שתעשיני כהן
גדול *al menas sheta'aseini kohen gadol*. You know, or teach me תורה
שבכתב *Torah shebichtav* and not תורה שבעל פה *Torah sheba'al peh*. שמאי
*Shamai* basically kicked him out, but you know this famous story, right?
And הלל *Hillel* accepts him and he becomes very פרום frum *frum*
and whatever. Okay. So everybody asks and רש"י Rashi, *Rashi* implicitly asks
and the מהרש"א *Maharsha* and everybody asks what do you mean it's
חוץ מדבר אחד *chutz midavar echad*? He shouldn't have accepted him. Besides
the question of whether the גירות *geirus* was good. חוץ מדבר אחד
*chutz midavar echad*, you should- and תוספות *Tosafos* says no, הלל *Hillel*
was סומך על חכמתו *somech al chochmoso* that this, you know, that
even though he was saying חוץ מדבר אחד *chutz midavar echad*, ultimately
he could have an effect on this person. And that leads to
a larger conversation about ultimately this is the discretion of the court
and whether it's the right move and whether it's for him and
for כלל ישראל *Klal Yisrael* and so on, you know, and it's
not just an absolute rule that you have to slam the door
like שמאי *Shamai* in front of everybody that says חוץ מדבר אחד
*chutz midavar echad*. So it's basically playing that גמרא *Gemara* off of
this גמרא *Gemara*. What?
But then you could say that vice versa.
Yeah, that somebody could be completely פרום *frum* and you still don't
think it's the right decision. Right, that is true.
Yeah. One quick thing, I mean the one thing we didn't address
here and is, and I know the גמרא *Gemara* in עבודה זרה
*Avodah Zarah* does, and maybe we'll get to it, is about whether
it was בצנעה *betzina* or בפרהסיה *befarhesia*.
So a little bit we'll talk about that. It's coming up. Yes,
so a little bit of that is coming up.
Because the here just says, right, חוץ מדבר אחד *chutz midavar echad*
and שלא כתורה כולה *shelo ketorah kula* and no one's differentiating between...
Right, so it's coming up a little bit. Right, so it's coming
up a little bit. So let's keep on going. So גמרא *Gemara*
says like this: וכן בן לוי שבא לקבל דברי לויה *Vechen ben
Levi sheba lekabel divrei Leviya* and a כהן *kohen* is that's a
little bit bizarre, you're born into being a לוי *Levi*, but presumably
it means that now you want to be accepted as a practicing
לוי *Levi* and you know, who knows, like do the singing in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash. *Beis HaMikdash*, what does it mean to
be a practicing לוי *Levi* nowadays, get שני *sheini*. Anyway, וכהן שבא
לקבל דברי כהונה *Vekohen sheba lekabel divrei kehuna* and a כהן *kohen*
that wants to now prepare himself and be accepted amongst the practicing
כהנים *kohanim* in the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, חוץ מדבר אחד *chutz
midavar echad*, but there's one thing I'm not prepared to do, אין
מקבלין אותו mekablin oto, *ein mekablino'to*, you do not accept them to
be function in that capacity, שנאמר המקריב את דם השלמים *Shene'emar hamakriv
es dam hashalmim*, somebody who offers up the blood of the שלמים
*shelamim*, לו יהיה חוק עולם למנה *lo yiheyeh chok olam lemaneh*, so
עבודה מסורה לבני אהרון *avodah mesura livnei Aharon*, כל כהן שאינו מודה
בה אין לו חלק chelek, בכהונה *kol kohen she'eino modeh bah ein
lo chelek bakehuna*. And it says so anything that is given over
to בני אהרון *Bnei Aharon*, if you do not accept it all,
you don't have a portion in the כהונה *kehuna*. The word חלק
chelek, *chelek* here is specific because when it talks about כהנים *kohanim*,
what it more excludes them from is getting a חלק chelek *chelek*
of the קרבנות *korbanos*, the... the dividing the קרבנות and the מתנות
כהונה, matnot kehunah, when it talks about the לוויים, leviyim, it talks
more about the fact that they are prevented from doing the service.
So there's an interesting question of what does it mean that they
are not accepted? Not accepted to get part of the benefits or,
you know, to get part of the מתנות, matnot, or does it
mean not accepted to actually do the service itself? Yes.
Can I still give my תרומה
to a כהן?
To this כהן who is not- Yeah,
well it means yes, because either way you read it basically when
it says it's a חלק, it means an entitlement to divide in
the חלק, like in the בית המקדש. I don't think- you know,
there's another discussion in the גמרא about המוחזיקין בתורת השם, hamachazikin betorat
Hashem, you know, you give the תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot to those
that are פרום, that are מחזיקין בתורת השם, machazikin betorat Hashem, but
that's not about מקבל דברי כהונה, mikabel divrei kehunah, that's about just
general פרומקייט. frumkeit. I think that if I remember correctly the way
it's understood about this חלק is specifically when things are מחולק, mechulak,
are divided up, and that you do get a portion amongst those.
Okay, let's keep on going, we have to make some tracks here.
So the גמרא says like this: תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הבא לקבל
דברי חברות, Haba lekabel divrei chaverut, שראינוהו שנוהג בצנעה, she'reinuho she'noheg betzina,
there's that. בתוך ביתו, betoch beito, מקבלין אותו, mekablin oto ואחר כך
מלמדין אותו. v'achar kach melamdin oto. So here is the sort of
the similar type of a question about a גר: how do we
know, you know, if somebody we suspect is somebody who's really going
to do it, going to live up to their responsibilities, but they're
not yet at that stage or they haven't gone through a formal
process? Can you accept them and assume that they will grow into
the practice? So if we saw that somebody was being פרום in
their house to the best of their knowledge, then you accept them
as a חבר chaver now and you don't wait until they've demonstrated
full compliance, and then because you assume that you'll train this person
and they will continue to grow. ואם לאו, ve'im lav, but if
we have not seen any practice until this point, first מלמדין אותו,
melamdin oto, you teach the person, you see that they're able to
live this life, that they have absorbed it and internalized it, ואחר
כך מקבלין אותו, v'achar kach mekablin oto, and then you accept them.
רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai אומר: בין כך ובין
כך bein kach u'vein kach מקבלין אותו mekablin oto. והולך כדרכו והולך,
ve'holech k'darko v'holech, which is a very beautiful sentiment from the same
רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai who had to go
into the cave because he was so judgmental. Maybe this was after
he came out of the cave. So he says, you know, take
people in, and by accepting them they'll grow, and then ultimately they
will- they will live up to those practices. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: מקבלין לכנפיים. mekablin lichnafayim. Now it's a funny phrase
כנפיים, knafayim, which means being careful about washing your hands before eating
and before חולין. Is it because wings are like, you know, your
hands are like wings? It's maybe sounds like
כפיים, kapayim, כנפיים, knafayim, כפיים, kapayim, all funny where that phrase comes
from.
What? Lyrical? It's very- yeah.
מקבלין לכנפיים. mekablin lichnafayim. Wings,
yeah. So if somebody accepts the פרומקייט frumkeit about the hands, so
fine, you can trust them then that they'll wash their hands before-
before- פרומקייט frumkeit anyway, the observance, you can trust them about that,
ואחר כך מקבלין לטהרות. ve'achar kach mekablin l'teharot. But then you can't
trust them yet to really be אוכל חולין בטהרה. ochel chulin betaharah.
You can trust them at the level that they wash their hands
before they ate. And then at a later stage, you know, they
can move up the ladder and even be believed in terms of
טהרות teharot if they accept that. ואם אמר: ve'im amar: איני מקבל
אלא לכנפיים, eini mekabel ela lichnafayim, and let's say he said, "I'm
not going up the ladder, I'm only going to do the handwashing
thing, I'm not going to try to be אוכל חולין בטהרה", ochel
chulin betaharah מקבלין אותו. You can accept them because that's a- that's
not one unit. It's not all or nothing. We can trust you
on that and that's separate, and you'll be trusted on that and
we don't treat it as one unit with the rest, where if
you're suspect for one, you're suspect for the other. קיבל לטהרות ולא
קיבל לכנפיים, kibel l'teharot velo kibel lichnafayim, but because it is lower
on the ladder, if somebody said, "I'm going to- I'm going to
do all of the טהרות teharot stuff but I'm not going to
wash the hands"- it's funny, how could you do the טהרות teharot
things without washing- but anyway, that's basically the point. אף לטהרות לא
קיבל. af l'teharot lo kibel. It's not meaningful, because that's lower on
the ladder. Okay, so you can do one step on the ladder
without the next step, but you can't do the higher step without
doing the lower step. Okay. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: עד מתי מקבלין
אותו. ad matai mekablin oto. Now the question is what exactly does
this mean? This prob- the way רש"י, Rashi the first explanation of
רש"י and the רמב"ם Rambam says it means is, after you've accepted
somebody, how long do you- you know there's implicit in this question
is that there's a probationary
period. And when- when does he move out of the probationary period
that not only has he been accepted but we can actually now
trust him in terms of his- in terms of תרומות ומעשרות, terumot
u'ma'asrot, טהרות, teharot, and so on? So let's just read this quickly.
בית שמאי אומרים: Beit Shammai omrim: למשקין שלושים יום. lemashkin shloshim yom.
When it comes to handling liquids and are they טומאה וטהרה tumah
v'taharah issues, which is a rabbinic concern with liquids, we can trust
them after thirty days of observance, a thirty-day probationary period. ולכסות שנים
עשר חודש. ule'chesut shneim asar chodesh. When it comes to their garments,
because the garments of עמי הארץ amei ha'aretz are considered to be
like garments of a זב zav and a זבה zavah and a
נידה, niddah, whatever, not very weighty the טומאה tumah there, so that
we have to wait till we've seen twelve months of observance. בית
הלל אומרים: Beit Hillel omrim: אחד בזה ואחד בזה שנים עשר חודש.
echad bezeh ve'echad bezeh shneim asar chodesh. Both need twelve months. ומה
דאמר: u'mah de'amar: אם כן הרי אלו מקולי בית שמאי ומחומרי בית
הלל. im ken harei elu mikulei Beit Shammai umichumrei Beit Hillel. If
that's true, it's a- it's a stringency of בית הלל. Beit Hillel.
Why isn't it listed amongst the stringencies of בית הלל? Beit Hillel?
אלא, ela, fine. בית הלל אומרים: Beit Hillel omrim: אחד בזה ואחד
בזה שלושים יום. echad bezeh ve'echad bezeh shloshim yom. Switch the text:
thirty-day probationary period. We will continue with this tomorrow.